Susan Porter Benson Papers
© 2011 University of Connecticut
Susan Porter Benson Papers.
undated, 1983-2005.
Archives & Special Collections at the Thomas J. Dodd Research Center.
Benson, Susan Porter, 1943-2005.
15.6 cubic feet.
The collection contains notes, manuscripts, syllabi, research materials, correspondence, ephemera and similar materials associated with the professional career of the historian, Susan Porter Benson, a member of the University of Connecticut faculty from 1993 until her death in 2005.
MSS20040071
Biography
The daughter of Alvin and Lorraine Porter, Susan Porter Benson was born in Washington, Pennsylvania, on July 26, 1943. She graduated from Simmons College (1964) and earned a Master's degree from Brown University (1968). She began teaching at Bristol Community College in 1968. She took leave to do labor education for the Amalgamated Clothing and Textile Worker's Union, funded by a grant from the National Endowment for the Humanities. In 1992, she received funding from NEH to write a book on how families make economic decisions, and in 2002 for a book examining how workers experienced their occupations and managed their work lives. Porter Benson earned a PhD in History from Boston University in 1983. She helped found a cooperative household on Hope Street in Providence, Rhode Island, a haven for aspiring historians. In addition to Bristol Community College (1968-1986), she taught at the University of Warwick, United Kingdom (1984), the University of Missouri-Columbia (1986-1993), Yale University (1998) before coming to the University of Connecticut in 1993 as director of the Women’s Studies Program. In 1998, she returned to full-time teaching and research in the history department at UConn.
The author of several books, many articles and co-editor of a special issue of Radical History Review, Porter Benson generated interest in the study of public history. The influential issue led to her co-editing, along with Stephen Brier and Roy Rosenzweig, of Presenting the Past: Essays on History and the Public (1986). This collection, in turn, inspired Critical Perspectives on the Past, the popular Temple University Press book series.
Susan Porter Benson died June 20, 2005.
Published Works:
Counter Cultures: Saleswomen, Managers, and Customers in American Department Stores, University of Illinois Press, 1986.
Presenting the Past: Essays on History and the Public,, 1986.
Who Built America? Working People and the Nation’s Economy, Politics, Culture and Society, Pantheon, 1992.
Household Accounts: Working-Class Family Economies in the Interwar USA, Cornell University Press, 2007.
Scope and Content
The collection contains notes, manuscripts, syllabi, research materials, correspondence, ephemera and similar materials associated with the professional career of the historian, Susan Porter Benson, a member of the University of Connecticut faculty from 1993 until her death in 2005.
Arrangement
Series I: Personal papers ( undated, 1983-1984 )
Series II: 2005 Addition ( undated, 1983-2005 )
Related Material
Archives & Special Collections has a substantial collection of materials pertaining to the University, its history, administration, faculty, staff and students. For detailed information on these collections please contact the curator or ask at the reference desk.
Index Terms
This record series is indexed under the following controlled access subject terms.
Persons:
Benson, Susan Porter, 1943-2005.
Organizations:
University of Connecticut.
Subjects:
Document Types:
Correspondence.; Publications.; Photographs.; Administrative Records.; Works of art.; Fliers. [printed matter]; Manuscripts.; Moving images.; Notes.
Occupations:
Historians.
Restrictions on Access
There are no access restrictions on this collection.
Acquisition Information
The materials in Series I were donated in 2004 by Dr. Benson. The remaining materials were transferred in 2005 by her family after her death.
Detailed Description of the Collection
- Series I: Personal papers, undated, 1983-1984
  - Personal files: Notes, manuscripts, correspondence, clippings, administrative records, publications, works of art and ephemera, undated, 1983-1984 (Box 1-4)
- Series II: 2005 Addition, undated, 1983-2005
  - Books, ephemera, notes, correspondence, clippings, financial records, undated, 1991 (Box 1)
    Topics include: Connecticut negotiation, AAA, working women, historical needle trades, leisure, class and gender, slavery, economy, industrial culture, urban amusements.
  - Notes, ephemera, works of art, books, clippings, undated, 1991 (Box 2)
    Topics include: women and education, Weaver--beyond Fordism, Victorian sexuality, women in Chesapeake, Antebellum black, Landcaster--New England, high heels, Mike Merrill, coffin, credit consumption, Chatterjee.
  - Publications, books, ephemera, fliers, correspondence, notes, administrative records, manuscripts, undated (Box 3)
    Topics include: OSV, research, railroad, Antebellum South, Asian-American women, strike, childhood, farm family, department stores, politics of the 1840s and 1850s, labor/politics/socialism in the 19th century, Lowell conference.
  - Notes, books, clippings, ephemera, publications, works of art, undated (Box 4)
    Topics include: economics, social aspects of the revolution, kazin, history, 1930s, 19th century.
  - Notes, correspondence, ephemera, administrative records, fliers, photographs, undated, 1994-1998 (Box 5)
    Topics include: McKendrick, History 401, weekly reports, Auslander, grades, New Jersey Turnpike, logistics, readings, EPT talk, backlash talk, multicultural group, Brown English procedures, women studies, E.P. Thompson.
  - Clippings, ephemera, correspondence, fliers, manuscript material, undated, 1998 (Box 6)
    Topics include: Africa, women, food retailing, US politics, international airlines, national airlines, airlines (general), Sears case, health, history, education, art, books, shopping, leisure, economy.
  - Notes, manuscripts, undated (Box 7)
    Topics include: southern textiles, milkman, labor, service, auto workers, women in World War II, popular culture, Leonardo, class, family and networks, freedman--hard hats, research of 1930s, 1960s, and 20th century, Braverman critiques, memory seminar, autobiography/subjectivity, 1980s history.
  - Financial records, notes, clippings, undated (Box 8)
    Topics include: Senate committee, nativism, mission hill, prostitution, printing, independent life histories (early 1900s), NY food riots, Hoover, Depression, 1920s, farm workers, prohibition, women labor unions, Italian immigrants.
  - Notes, ephemera, manuscripts, books, correspondence, administrative records, publications, undated, 1998-2000 (Box 9)
    Topics include: history, Deutsch, Connecticut economy.
  - Fliers, notes, ephemera, correspondence, clippings, undated, 1998-1999 (Box 10)
    Topics include: Palmer, rights, politics, suffrage, graduate student evaluations, syllabi, Cameron, logistics, Assman, Sutherland, Cohen, Neisser, Hewitt, material culture, mobility studies, oral history, reading notes, history introduction, Dublin, sexuality/lesbians, bonds of women hood, Pascoe, anthropology.
  - Books, notes, undated, 1989-2005 (Box 11)
    Topics include: Dust Bowl, women's studies, gay/lesbian history, co-op, gender and history, public history, USDA, Martin Guerre, Jefferson-Hemmings, compulsory heterosexuality, UConn student evaluations, emancipation of women.
  - Moving images, notes, undated, 2005 (Box 12)
    Topics include: German Historical Institute, Scott, Deutsch, Leavitt, Dubois, Douglas - "I'm not a feminist, but…", Hoikkala: Mothers and Community Builders, Harley, social feminism.